And just like that, Swiss bond rates are
almost back at zero all over again. The
critical two-year instrument yielding
just a couple of basis points, and it's
very likely to go negative very soon.
Now, as we know, Swiss interest rates
have very little to do with Switzerland.
As a global money center, this is where
money goes when it doesn't want to be
anywhere else to the point that all of
these international financial firms are
willing to accept zero and maybe even
negative rates to be there. It's not
just Switzerland, either. Chinese rates
are similarly ultra and that curve is
bull steepening. Now, not as low as the
Swiss, but very much in the same
ballpark. China is a huge yet
unappreciated bond market, largely
because most people wrongly believe
trading is deterred by the central
government in Beijing, and rates are set
by the central bank, the PBOC. The
signal from the Chinese bonds, however,
is far more integrated to the global
system than you think. There is a lot of
globally synchronized in it. There'd be
a lot more, except central bankers in
other places like Frankfurt with the
ECB, and yes, DC with the Fed and its
utterly ridiculous thoughts. They're all
interfering with those markets. And this
is the part central bankers and other
financial media keep trying to avoid. In
the US, Europe, Australia, and plenty of
other places, policy rates are still
being held up by officials who continue
talking about inflation risks, sticky
prices, and the need to remain cautious.
But where the market is allowed to speak
more clearly, the message is very clear
and getting clearer all the time. These
unfiltered markets share a lot more in
common with other yield curves, too,
such as the clear flattening in US
Treasuries, as we'll see here. In other
words, there is more Switzerland and
China in USTs than you've been told
because the story is always framed from
the central bank perspective first.
That's not just backward, in this case,
it's beyond cliché.
Steve, Switzerland, rates almost back to
zero, almost back to going negative
again. China, bull steepening on that
curve, and the two the two the common
variable between the two of them is you
don't have these central banks going
over going off on inflation inflation
risk that obviously doesn't exist.
>> Yeah, Jeff, it's kind of interesting
because it wasn't long ago people said
rates will never get back to zero. It's
never going to happen. We're in a new
regime. It's higher is the normal. And
here Switzerland is pretty much right
back at zero as you said, going
negative. And you start to look around
the world and the reality is, and I
think a lot of people are struggling
this particularly here in the US because
the economy looks you relatively good
compared to the rest of the world. You
know, stock market is up, spending seems
to be holding up a bit, you know, and
yet what is the bond market telling us
in Switzerland? That this energy shock
is real and that even if you lower
interest rates to zero, it's not going
to make any difference and that's the
problem. You know, everyone's going to
look to central bankers as the global
economy slows down and the reality is
that I think this has a lot to do with
why we're really not hearing from the
PBOC right now is very simple. Look,
they could raise rates, they could lower
rates, they could just get rid of the
entire central bank and it won't stop
the damage that's already happened. So,
the reality is are rates going to
continue to drop and go negative?
Absolutely. Will central bankers panic?
Absolutely. Is it going to work? I don't
think it's going to work.
>> Yeah, that's the common the other common
theme between Switzerland and China.
Switzerland rates are low heading
negative like you said, but China rates
there are ultra low to begin with as
well. The one year Chinese government
bond yield is almost back to 1% again,
which which it was below briefly back in
late 2024 when there's all sorts over
tariff and you know, trade wars that
were developing at the time. So, rates
are ultra low
in large part because central banks in
both of those places are not interfering
in the rates markets. Now, look at what
happens when they do interfere in the
rates markets. Then you got, you know,
Europe is a prime example where the
European Central Bank just raised its
policy rates and its policy rate
corridor, which has flattened out the
yield curve. We saw the same thing to a
a extent here in the United States this
past week when the Federal Reserve
didn't raise rates but the the overall
posture at least the perception of the
posture of the Federal Open Market
Committee was that it's more hawkish
than now. We got that out of the
ridiculous dots and the stripped-down
version of the FOMC statement that just
said we are not going to allow inflation
or something along those lines. So, we
got somewhat of a hawkish lean from the
Federal Open Market Committee from the
Federal Reserve like
like we see in Europe. And what happened
to the yield curve? Well, short-term
rates went up at least the you know the
middle part of the curve the front part
of the middle curve. Two-year Treasury
yield goes out but the rest of the curve
flattens out which means you take away
the central bank and suddenly the yield
curve in US Treasuries or the yield
curve in German bonds or French oats or
whatever in Europe would probably look a
hell of a lot more like we see taking
place in China and Switzerland. If you
have a retirement account and if you've
ever wondered whether crypto belongs
inside of it, BlockTrust IRA is
something worth looking into. Now, most
crypto IRA platforms are self-directed.
They give you access but you have to
decide what to buy, when to sell, when
to rebalance. BlockTrust IRA is
different. It's designed as a managed
crypto IRA solution meaning there's a
portfolio strategy behind the account.
Custody is provided through SFOX and the
strategy includes active portfolio
management and rebalancing inside the
IRA. Now, BlockTrust IRA states that its
portfolio system has outperformed
Bitcoin buy and hold by over 250
percentage points since 2020. Now, past
performance does not guarantee future
results and crypto investments can
indeed lose value including principal.
Now, right now eligible viewers can get
up to a $2,500 crypto bonus when they
open and fund an account. Terms,
conditions, funding minimums, and
eligibility requirements apply. To learn
more, go to youradollar.crypto.com.
Now, this is a paid advertisement not
financial, investment, tax, or
retirement advice. Crypto is volatile
and may lose value and past performance
is no guarantee of future results. Plus,
terms do apply.
>> Yeah, absolutely, Jeff. And I thought
really the reaction from the bond
market, particularly after Kevin Warsh,
you know, his press conference, was
really telling because the market was
simply reacting to, "Well, we don't know
what he's going to do, but he's admitted
that he doesn't like the balance sheet.
So, we know he's really not going to
touch that." Given him one tool, that's
of course the funds rate. And since he's
acting like we're going to squish
inflation, we're going to bring this
thing right back down, he's got to raise
rates. And then look at the market
reaction after that. Front of the curve
goes up, which makes sense because it's
sensitive to changes in the fund rate,
and the market wants to get ahead of it.
But the long end of the curve was
saying, "Wait a minute. Hold on here. Uh
this move is not good because we're
facing a supply shock, and this is going
to go and put us right into the same
place we've been before when we have
energy shocks. We've got four out of
five of them that put us in recession."
And the bond market on the long of the
curve clearly saying, "Look, you can do
whatever you want in the short term, but
growth and inflation expectations now
are clearly headed to the downside."
>> Yeah, that's the key part about
Switzerland cuz you have growth and
inflation expectations around the rest
of the world from the Swiss perspective,
which is a unique perspective,
admittedly, but still, it's not really
about Switzerland, it's not really about
demand for specifically the bonds that
are issued by the you know, the
federation in Switzerland. It's It's
about when I don't really perceive a lot
of appetite to go out there in the
global system and buy some risky assets,
I mean, other than you know,
semiconductor stocks or something like
that. When I'm really kind of um really
kind of in a risk-averse mood, I'm just
going to park my money in Switzerland
because it's it's easy, it's safe, it's
mostly anonymous and private. It's It's
got all the stuff that makes the Swiss
bank banking system a money center. So,
when you see money flow into
Switzerland, despite the fact there is
basically no yield in doing it, right? I
mean, you're you're getting into a stock
that's or getting into the stock. You're
getting into a currency that's way up
here to begin with. The value is
relatively high. You've got basically no
yield in the government bonds, yet we
see an overwhelming flood of money going
into Swiss government bonds, which same
as anywhere else. When demand for safety
and liquidity goes up this much, it
tells you that the perceptions of safety
and liquidity around the rest of the
world are moving in the wrong direction,
at least the wrong way from inflation or
even just reflation. They're moving in
the direction as as Steve said, for a
world that is likely facing some degree
of economic fallout after the energy
shock, which comes along on top of a
weak economic situation that we were
dealing with to begin with because bond
rates were heading lower before all this
you know, the oil shock really showed up
in the Iran conflict.
>> Yeah, and Jeff, you know, you think
about the oil shock and you particularly
here in the US and we look at the
difference between as you said, people
in other parts of world are seeking
safety, they're seeking liquidity. Here,
you know, people are looking at the
stock market and say, "Well, hey, look,
the economy wasn't that impacted." And
and why not? I mean, everyone's been
saying we're going to have this energy
shock, it's going to be dangerous, it's
going to bring the you know, economy and
the market to its knees. But, it's a
delayed effect. And I think that's the
challenge here. You know, there is a
certain part of the population saying,
"What do you mean there's no shock? I
feel it every day. You know, I go to
Walmart and you know, we talked about
this before. They're putting you know,
they're going to the store and then
they're going and putting less than $10
of gas in their car. They just don't
have the money. So, the shock is
growing, it's real. But, for a lot of
people, they look around the economy and
they say, "Well, spending's up, market's
up. It can't be that bad." It's just the
delayed effect of when it catches up.
And the rest of world is telling us
because they got hit far harder and far
faster than we did, that look, the shock
we're facing is the same shock you're
going to hit with. And yet Kevin Warsh
suddenly worried about inflation. But
the reality is Jeff, that's the last
thing he really should be worried about
right now.
>> Yeah, that's a key that's a really good
point Steve, the timing here. Uh because
there is you know, there's definitely a
delayed effect. I mean, even economists
talk about interest rates with long and
variable lags. It's the same thing with
anything, you know, something happens,
it doesn't doesn't you know, the
consequence doesn't show up right away.
But there is that perception that's how
it works, right? We've seen this a
couple of different times. The idea was
uh-oh, there's an Iran there's going to
be a war with Iran, they're closing off
the Straits of Hormuz. Oh my god, the
world is about to collapse, there's no
oil flowing, you know, we've got 20% of
daily global needs that just gets
bottled up. And then you even saw the
stock market as the stock market sells
off through March. And then in early
April it's like, wait a minute, the
world didn't collapse, so therefore
everything must be perfectly fine. Bye
bye bye bye bye. That's That's the
attitude that you know, it's it's not
even a short attention span, it's just a
short time frame that you you only give
the the you give the the energy shock
just a single a couple of weeks to to to
produce the worst case. And if it
doesn't produce the worst case, then the
the worst case must be completely off
the table, and everybody goes back to
re-risking all over again. And that's
really I think we've seen that that's
one of the reasons why I wanted to bring
up the Swiss bond market as well as the
Chinese bond market is is
because they have more pure they have
pure signals about interest rates,
growth and inflation expectations,
liquidity demands. They're looking
through any central bank interference,
any central bank policy interference at
those growth and inflation expectations
from the near term all the way out to
the long run. And what those bond
markets are saying without these
interference, and from their position
which is much closer to the damage and
much closer to the timeline for the
energy shock, what they're saying is
this looks like an energy shock. This
looks like the follow. We've got Swiss
rates that are almost back into the
negatives again. You have the Chinese
Chinese curve that is ultra low
territory to begin with yet continues to
bull steeping. And it's it fits with
that overall characterization. You take
the central banks out of the equation,
get them out of the media, it suddenly
the world looks very different. It
certainly looks a lot different than the
Philadelphia semiconductor index.
>> Yeah, quite a bit different than that.
But, you know, let's talk about China
because, you know, it wasn't long ago
that Beijing was telling the banks to
stop buying bonds, you're going to get
slaughtered when rates go up because we
want rates to go up. And now all of a
sudden everybody is quiet.
>> Just to be clear here. Let's be Let's be
clear here. In 2024, the PBOC didn't
just tell banks to stop buying bonds.
They threatened them. They threatened
them with exposing their clients who
were buying bonds. They went to
absolutely, you know, egregious tactics
to try to get the the banking sector
brokers. They They They threatened to,
you know, extra regulatory. They went
nuts trying to get banks not to buy
bonds.
>> And so why is that shifting now? Well,
we've known for the last couple of years
their economy has been decelerating.
They're at a point that it's unlikely
they're going to escape this, you know,
no matter what they do. So, why would
the government all of a sudden get quiet
about interest rates? Even though
they're talking a lot about liquidity,
but their answer now is, "Well, we want
to make sure there's enough liquidity."
And why is that? They want more money to
go into the banking system. They're
going to want rates to go lower because
the PBOC, and this is I think this is
what we're going to see from governments
all around the world, is "Hey, if rates
can get low enough, we're going to
borrow a ton of money and we're going to
do a ton of stimulus because there's no
other path out of this. There's no way
that you I mean, you could drop rates to
minus 5%. It's not going to fix the
energy shock because the people that are
impacted by this, they're not in a place
where they're borrowing anyways. They're
wondering how they're going to get from
one paycheck to the next." So, then how
you know, then you look at the business
perspective. They're saying, "How am I
going to sell this inventory if people
can't afford it?" Wages keep
decelerating. Everything looked bad. So,
you start thinking about why they're
quiet. I think, Jeff, it's simply they
want to do a lot of stimulus and they're
looking for people to help fund it.
>> And you really need to look at all these
various different global signals to be
able to have any idea what's happening,
say, here in the United States because
we live in a globally synchronized world
far more than you've ever been taught or
told. And that's why we're having our
webinar next Sunday, June 28th, 5:30
p.m. Eastern Time, Euro Dollar
University. We're going to go over how
to make an all-weather portfolio
strategy out of useful signals that
almost no one knows is are out there and
fewer still know how to use properly,
how to interpret them. And this is
understandable because you've been
taught basically everything backward. I
mean, people often fall into the trap of
thinking nationally and it's no wonder
because that's the message that you get.
So, join us next Sunday, June 28th, 5:30
p.m. Eastern. We're going to break down
how to unlock all the secret information
that very few people follow even fewer
actually understand. All the stuff that
we can't get into here on YouTube, we're
going to go deeper into them and put
them into an investment portfolio
management strategy context. Don't just
react to the markets. Learn to read what
they're already telling you. So, again,
join me next Sunday, June 28th, 5:30
p.m. Eastern. There's a link in the
description to sign up.
>> Yeah, the
the the I did the video on this
yesterday where the Chinese have
essentially the bond market in China has
overtaken Chinese bank lending in terms
of credit creation at the margins.
Which, I mean, you know, some people in
the media are celebrating as some kind
of, you know, maturation of the Chinese
financial system when this is another
sign of depression economics. We went
through this in the United States and to
an extent in Europe, but definitely in
the United States. In the immediate
aftermath of the 2008 crisis, um the
bond market in many ways bailed out the
system more than certainly more than the
Federal Reserve did. The Federal Reserve
didn't really do much at all. It was the
bond market that limited the damage in
the downside. However, that was
sacrificing bank lending so that there
was no upside. This is depression
economics. When financial participants
want safety and liquidity, whether it be
in Switzerland or in China, that's not a
good sign. When when you're when you're
that risk averse where you only want to
you only want to own government security
because it's the safest and perceived to
be the safest and most liquid, you're
not going to do anything else in the
real economy, which by the way is what
lower interest rates are supposed to do.
Let's Let's set aside the realistic
objections that low interest rates
aren't stimulus. The reason they're not
stimulus is because of safety and
liquidity demand. But let's let's assume
that they are. What central bankers and
economists are trying to say by lowering
lowering interest rates to Steve's point
here, what they're hoping is that there
are some healthy account or some some
healthy businesses out there who will
see lower rates and say, "You know what?
I'm going to I'm going to borrow because
rates are low. I'm going to do what I
wasn't going to do before. I'm going to
borrow a little bit. I'm going to add a
little bit to my production. I might
have to hire a couple of people." And if
you get enough healthy businesses that
suddenly want to borrow because rates
are lower, then at the margins you start
to see a little bit more of economic
activity that leads into further
economic activity. This is the Keynesian
virtuous cycle that then leads to more
hiring, more more income, more spending.
That's what's supposed to happen. But
assuming that it actually does happen,
we don't we
everybody else ignores what happens on
the other side of that. Well, for every
borrower there has to be a lender. And
if the lender is saying, "You know what?
I just want to own government bonds. It
doesn't matter how low rates go because
they're saying I want safety and
liquidity. I'm not going to lend to that
person over there, even if they are a
healthy business. I probably don't want
to take the liquidity risk to do so." So
even as rates go down, you don't have
that stimulative effect. Instead, what
you have is the marketplace telling you
the marketplace itself is not optimistic
about the future. Certainly not
inflationary, but it's also not
reflationary, either.
>> Yeah, Jeff, and that's you know, you
look at these people that are you know,
buying effectively zero yielding
government debt and it's like everyone's
like, "But what about inflation?" If
they were worried about inflation, then
they wouldn't be buying it. Because the
reality is they know that inflation is
going to come back down and at this
point, they don't want to put their
money in the currencies, they don't want
to put their money in, you know, the
stock market. They just want their money
back. And that's a big tell because when
someone is not willing to put their
capital at risk just to get it back down
the road for a very small return, it
tells you everything about what these
people are saying about the real
economy, inflation, currencies, central
bank. It tells you everything you need
to know.
>> Yeah, and we see that here again, let's
go back to the Treasury curve. That
point is like you said, Steve, if if the
market was convinced that oil prices
were going to be inflationary, the last
thing that you would want to own is a
30-year Treasury bond. You would be
ditching that thing and I mean, you
you'd be on the phone with the broker
tomorrow to do it to do something like
that. You don't want to own safety and
liquidity when you're in an inflationary
environment. This is again another
another part that people don't really
understand or don't really get. In
inflationary periods, rates go up
because you don't want to own safety and
liquidity. If you have a genuinely
inflationary environment, you want to be
out there in the real economy generating
high nominal returns because if there's
inflation, nominal returns are going to
be higher and higher and higher. So, you
don't want to own a government bond, you
want to do, you know, some real economy
loan to some smaller company that you
think is reasonably sure to pay it back
cuz you're going to get double digits or
maybe even better returns, at least
nominal returns on your money.
If there was an inflationary impulse, we
would see the yield curve on Treasuries
steepen out. If if there was any threat
whatsoever, the yield curve would
steepen out. But as central banks,
including now the Federal Reserve, have
threatened to raise rates over inflation
that they think they see, the yield
curve is instead flattened. Not only
flattened, it has flattened
dramatically.
The one spread that people pay attention
to, you actually should pay attention to
all the spreads, but one the one spread
people pay attention to is the
difference between the two-year and the
10-year. I was, you know, what what most
people know is that when the two-year
10-year inverts, it's usually a
recession signal. It's not always about
recession, but it's it's a key signal
that people watch on the yield curve.
Well, as this has developed over the
last couple weeks, the two-year has gone
up, the 10-year has gone basically
nowhere, the 30-year has actually kind
of did gone down a little bit. The long
end has been basically the same as the
two-year go the two-year 10-year spread
is down to about 25 basis points. It is
more in danger of reinverting than it is
signaling something like inflation. And
that flattening of the yield curve is
every bit consistent with Swiss bond
rates that are heading towards zero and
negative and a Chinese bull steepening
curve that continues to bull steepen at
ultra-low rates with no central bank
interference from the PBOC.
>> Yeah, and just of those who use to
understand, you know, the the curve of
the curve is trying to tell us is on the
front end of the two side is saying,
"Hey, look, central bankers are going to
raise rates." The 10's the long end is
saying, "Wait a minute, growth is
inflation expectations are going down.
And so, what it's trying to say is
there's a big warning sign here, central
bankers." Now, we're not trying to say
here that central bankers are making the
right move and that lowering rates would
do something. What it's just implying
is, "Look, there's a huge mistake. Rates
need to be going down and the bond
market is trying to very clearly tell
all the policy makers anywhere who will
listen is you need to lower rates here
if you have any hope of this working."
>> Yeah, it's about what rates actually
are. It's not a lever for control over
the economy or even financial markets or
even lending. It's information from the
marketplace, which by the way, these
are, you know, it's a very sophisticated
and highly integrated global
marketplace. When we talk about Swiss
bonds, we're not really talking about
Switzerland. Even when we talk about
Chinese bonds and the Chinese bond
curve, we're not really talking about
China. The Chinese system is much more
integrated into the global bond market
and the global financial system than
people give it credit for, and that's
pun intended. Um, so you look at the
Chinese bond market and you're not just
getting Chinese, you know, fears over
the Chinese economy, you're also getting
perceptions about how China's economy
fits within that that over global the
overall global framework. Same thing
with Switzerland. In fact, in
Switzerland, it's a thousand times worse
because Switzerland is such Switzerland
itself is such a tiny economy, it's
almost exclusively about global factors.
So, when you remove the central bank
variable, this is what you get. You get
Swiss yields that are heading toward
negative again. You get Chinese bond
rates that are ultra low and getting
lower all the time. And you got central
bankers that are talking about inflation
that even their curves that are, you
know, local to them like US Treasuries
or German bonds in Europe, those curves
continue to flatten out. All of it is
this basically the same signal from
different perspectives based on, you
know, whether or not central banks are
interfering or central banks are on the
sidelines. And what the bond market is
saying very clearly, and we see this in
the TIPS market,
perfectly clear. There is no inflation
risk. If anything, the inflation risk
what what little there was to begin with
has gone completely away. And so the
market is now saying with that that
behind us, now we don't have higher oil
prices, at least we think and we hope
that we don't have higher oil prices,
the next thing is what did these past
oil prices do to economic prospects?
>> And you Jeff, you made a very key point
here then and I think this ties
everything back from where we started is
if we didn't have central bank
intervention here say in Europe or in
the US or other parts where they're very
hawkish right now and we looked at
Switzerland and we looked at China, what
would it be telling us? Is the
short-term rates would be plunging right
back to zero. And what the two tens
curve is telling us is that's exactly
what's going to happen. So, the bond
market is being very clear here. We know
what's coming. Of course, the risk is
and as you know this if the curve does
invert and it's looking like that's a
high probability, it's the stock market
that everyone's chasing to the upside is
also going to face a day of reckoning
because once we invert again here, now
the risk of a recession and or a
financial crisis, all the bad things
that come from it start to go up and
very quickly at that point if changing
the federal funds rate could work, it
did work. At this point, it's far too
late and Kevin Warsh once again stepping
into a massive policy mistake that he
seems to think is all about money money
supply inflation when he can't see the
real shock that's impacting everyday
Americans.